hmm
i
tried to
record a similar video
uh last week
i mean i've tried to record this video
many times essentially kind of just a
general
depression what's what's depression all
about what's it like what's it like to
experience it i think where i go wrong
is
trying to um
trying to record this on days that i
feel depressed today i feel okay
today is not a depression day as i
sometimes call him
uh
it's more difficult to access
fluidity and
thought without
like a meanness to it i guess when
you're depressed there's uh me i get
like neural inflammation
uh
which is like
you know you kind of get brain fog just
kind of it's hard to remember things
sometimes you like mispronounce things
uh you don't have a lot of energy for
conversations or even
like
bringing any sort of intellect to
conversations it's just in a contrast of
feeling feeling you know pretty dang
good everything's going good
everything's clear you don't feel
constricted you feel open you feel
fluent with the people you're around
you're having you know easy verbal
fluency you're not thinking about what
you're doing you're present
that is very different it's very hard to
grasp that
when you are depressed when you have uh
you know a depression day or you know
especially if you're having brain fog
and uh neural inflammation
so
in my last video i i uh i haven't
watched it back because i thought it was
it was awful and i felt terrible the
whole time about it uh but i just wanted
to record it right so maybe it's a rough
draft at this point um i kept repeating
that depression is not sadness
depression is not really even extreme
sadness
sadness is like a symptom it's like one
of the things that comes with depression
but i think um
oh and you know i am going to talk about
anxiety as well that is a a part of this
but so depression is a
how is it not sadness i think that that
is a an important part because someone
who doesn't experience depression
what you know a lot of times
you know if you have a loved one who's
experiencing depression you're trying to
emphasize you're trying to like
you're really trying to understand what
they're going through but
the worst
you've ever felt is the worst you've
ever felt i mean you
you can only think of the worst you have
have ever felt i mean immediately this
is like
so overly complicated so
depression is not sadness not just
sadness uh because it's kind of an
inability to plan your way out of how
you're feeling
sadness is it you know a lot of times
when someone's depressed someone will
say well what's wrong why are you
depressed what's like what's going on
it's not often just a situation it's not
often just like at one thing in your
life that you're ruminating about that's
uh that's eaten you and it's like i
can't cope with this specific situation
um
depression has kind of this like
it has flavors to it it's like a
nihilism
meaning uh you're kind of just negative
about all your future plans you're
negative about what's going on
the things that you typically like
you you're not going to like on these
days
when i say these days i'm just coming
back to like depression days you know
like like
i think it's helpful
uh maybe it'll be confusing at first but
i think it will be helpful to
uh come back to comparing like a good
day
for me versus a depression day because
it's just two very different
beings you know it's it's it's two very
different um
very different ways of of how i show up
to myself and and
in social and in friend family
interactions
so
it has this nihilism it has this uh kind
of negative attitude towards things so
it's like
yes you're
sad maybe you can start to pinpoint okay
there's this thing that triggered me
this one thing got me going
uh you know you i think your brain will
always find
hey why is it that i'm sad okay what the
[__] is going on like why am i
why am i a depressed sad boy today and i
think it is easy to
pick something or find ways in which you
are inadequate especially of late
um
you know i think we have that internal
uh
you know moderator our internal
narrator uh is kind of
kind of like hard on us sometimes like
sometimes we're hard on ourselves
sometimes we um we're over the analytic
i mean because look we're you know we're
all human we're all
made of mistakes we're all
trying to figure this thing out like
none of us you know remember
asking to be here we just kind of like
you grow up and then you start to become
a teenager and you're like well [__] i
gotta okay like i gotta take life by the
horns like i didn't ask to be alive but
here i am you know we're all kind of
like learning what it means to be human
uh ronda says we're all just walking one
another home we're all just walking each
other home
you know uh life is kind of this uh
it's kind of uh this sounds more but
it's not supposed to be uh uh it's kind
of a
the path to death
you know it's this is such a immense
wild thing here you know uh that
it's hard to
i guess i guess i'm trying to say it's
like we shouldn't we shouldn't be so
hard on ourselves and you know there's
this hard voice that's like hey you
didn't know exactly how this was going
to turn out uh you didn't predict the
future you didn't do exactly what you
wanted i mean because
wouldn't you who would choose to feel
depression who would choose to feel
anxiety he would choose to feel pain you
know
their um
their
their feelings that
their things that our body uh kind of
generate you know this this physical
meat pod here generates
um
certain
ways of clenching up certain
chemicals are released when when
specific things happened you know
there's there's a reason to
you know they say anxiety is is uh
you know fear for the future you're
thinking about what might happen in the
future and depression is uh you know can
can be considered
you are upset about what happened in the
past um a lot of depression seems kind
of like
uh the shame to it you know there's
guilt to it there's i wish i knew better
and i wish i did this thing differently
and sometimes you can even bring it to
the present like look all these things
around me like
oh i you know
this is where i've gotten myself you
know all this all this
[__] in the past that i did got me to
exactly where i'm at here you know that
could be very
uh
you know
to to notice such thing to notice
that
you know we have so much momentum
where we're going this is how life works
we're
you know we were young kids we were in
school and they say hey you know get get
through sixth grade and then you go to
middle school cool and then after middle
school you're gonna go to high school
and after high school you're gonna go to
college and after that you're gonna go
to you know after
after graduate or what they call some
stupid uh uh
postgraduate degrees or or whatever uh
that you could go get a job and there's
always this there is this sense in the
western world the way we were all kind
of raised there's this sense of um
of
like going like like we're gonna reach
this place
like we're going to arrive
there is a sense in our way of being
as humans that we're going to get to
this spot we're going to get to this
place where we don't feel
you know fear shame
guilt uh sadness uh
like we're just gonna
get to uh you know we don't have to go
to work we don't have any obligations we
don't we don't have to repaint the spare
bedroom you know we don't have to wash
the dishes
uh
there is kind of this thing in the back
of a lot of our heads
that we're going to arrive
in life you know alan watts you know
very elegantly speaks of life being kind
of a dance life is not
uh
uh getting from this
this part of the room to the other side
of the room at a certain speed
and with a certain
uh
punctuation
we don't arrive at the other side of the
room life is the dance in between life
is the
is the breezy uh movement with the music
and the environment and the uh
you know the the eye contact in the in
the present moment the non-thinking the
joy that is experienced
when dancing in a room you know when
there's other people around
it's not uh alan watts also speaks of
you know
the greatest conductors are not those
who play the fastest or those who have
the the loudest ending you know
there's something in our heads in the
western world that has kind of trained
us to think i'm going to get somewhere
i'm going to arrive at this place
and this is where anxiety and depression
come in because
you are
anxious about what may happen and what
may not happen you're anxious about
living incorrectly
um you have
fear that this thing might happen like
like right now in the present moment
here and now the thing you you have you
know visual pictures
and uh words however the way in which
you think
you have this
projection of
based off of the information you have
now you're trying to put together these
patterns into okay well this thing is
clearly going to happen i don't want it
to happen i'm incapable of handling it
when it does happen
so we could be ruminating we could be uh
really kind of caught in our heads
uh and uh there is levels of anxiety
even
even reaching back i i speak about you
know uh
the the past the
shame the guilt aspects of depression
looking back into the past um uh wishing
wishing you had just done things
differently wishing you had
wishing
trying to
make your body right now feel sad like
these chemicals are being released when
you're sitting here if you're just
sitting there staring at the wall like
thinking about
uh you know when you got a [__] dui
five years ago and you had to pay all
this money and your baby mama left you
and you know
these things life happens you know we're
all we all have our [__] right
there is you're sitting in the present
moment you're right here
thinking
of something
that
has already happened
you're you're kind of recalling and
repeating and reliving
this situation
that uh
you know there is a part of you that
wants to learn from it you're thinking
to yourself why did i do that like why
like why would i choose to what the hell
um
there
it's it's
it's human
it is human
it's not that abnormal a lot of people
are doing this i mean we're all kind of
a basket case in our head really if you
stop and just observe your thoughts as
they're passing by you're you're a damn
mad person
you know we're all
we're all pretty nutty as it turns out
we just have this external facade that
we all have to play along with we have
this cultural zeitgeist that we have to
um
you know keep faced with we have our
customer service mask our coffee shop
face
uh and it's it's it's part of being a
human it's part of having an ego it's
part of uh uh uh
you know experiencing life
and having um you know we have to have a
societal avatar
to exist it will like there would be no
personality to you if you didn't have um
an an ego or a uh a projection of
your interactions with others how it
makes you feel
and
you know kind of a
what you believe others think of you
kind of creates a lot of what our ego is
and a lot of what our internal dialogue
is with ourselves
so
we could be depressed thinking about
something that's not here you know but
so so what we have to do
for me
i started noticing these things that's a
huge part is being aware not being
caught in the thought right so when
you're when you're having an anxiety
attack when you're having um
let's back up let's not talk anxiety
attacks yet i will get to those but
let's say we're just having an anxious
feeling you're having that you know
maybe um
what is a what does a relaxed person
look like you know maybe you know their
face isn't all tensed up their shoulders
are down your shoulders are are back
they're comfortable imagine how you may
feel uh you know when you're at at a
family event you know you have no reason
to be anyone other than yourself you can
laugh you know you're very comfortable
with what's going on you don't feel
threatened in any way
you're relaxed your your your body
language um
you're kind of unconsciously doing
certain things you know your feet are
even uh facing your loved ones um if
you know there's there is this general
openness
um there's a lot of great research on
lobsters actually when it comes to
serotonin there is a
higher levels of serotonin when we are
kind of relaxed and
and opened in our shoulders our back uh
lobsters actually when you
take away their serotonin if they are
the alpha lobster at the top of the tank
you take away their serotonin they
actually kind of close back in and they
sink to the bottom of the tank so
there's a hierarchy with lobsters that
we've tested kind of how serotonin works
i think it's serotonin that it is um
it's good stuff though i'm sure you can
find that if that interests you
lobsters serotonin depression
hierarchy something you'll find it um
so
there's also
so so
so oh the opposite so yeah we're open up
um
this is how we feel when when we're open
we're ready you know you're comfortable
with where you at you're comfortable
with yourself and what you're there to
do
versus think of someone who is depressed
you know what what do they look like
maybe they've you know i mean maybe you
think of someone with their hood up
maybe you think of a
kind of kind of a more of a closed off
physical stature posture uh maybe your
shoulders kind of humped up
humped over
you know maybe their feet are kind of
facing in maybe they're trying to appear
small
this is kind of an unconscious thing
that a lot of us that that's going to
happen this is this is how you get when
you're depressed you know you're kind of
closed off
uh
when you think about when you're anxious
you know there is an aspect of kind of
like wanting to appear small you know
but even sometimes anxiousness is
busy anxious you know it is you are open
um but think about your shoulders is a
great one you know your jaw your um all
this muscle muscle tension your eyes you
know if you're anxious you might be like
okay okay let's go we gotta do this
thing and maybe you're kind of moving
fast maybe you're breathing if you
notice you're breathing maybe your
breathing is up here in your chest when
you're anxious um or when you're overly
ruminating about the past or or the or
the future so
what one thing you want to try to do
one thing you want to remember is when
we can become aware of these things
what is my body doing okay i'm thinking
about this thing oh the the mind is
ruminating over the past again there i
go again there
there the mind goes oh how human i am
okay forgive yourself you know because
we'll judge ourselves a lot for even
having these thoughts for even having if
you have intrusive thoughts i've had
i've dealt with a ton of intrusive
thoughts and i thought i was the worst
person ever and it got i would
there was this reaction that i would
have to intrusive thoughts uh that would
be kind of
um
like a
like a tick
in response to the intrusive thought and
this is something that i've that i've
cleared up with um i think a lot of this
this work around mindfulness and
meditation and uh yoga breath work a lot
of the stuff that i'm kind of
trying to bring into the conversation
here
um
is
i think it's kind of eliminated a lot of
these kind of tics that i had you know a
lot of these
uh
things that i would do physically kind
of unconsciously
they would just happen when i was not
getting my preference when i um it's
kind of like like you know you might
hear of ocd these sorts of things i
think a lot of us overly diagnose
ourselves with ocd it's kind of this
casual buzzfeed word in a lot of ways
but it's actually not
i don't think that it's helpful to
attach these things to our identity all
the time maybe to open up conversations
and understand ourselves but i think
that you know as we discovered these
you know
our own neurosurg neuroses which we all
have
i think there's so much information out
here and there's so many ways to learn
about what's happening rather than just
sitting and suffering with what we're
experiencing that we can kind of over
time with patients with you know
perseverance with work with actual doing
things work
i think we can kind of unwind these
things i used to be someone who would
consider himself someone who i i would
tell people i have ocd um there's
certain things that people my loved ones
would know about me like you know the
the simple there's a great example that
i'm sure a lot of people you stress
about
being an even number when you're turning
up the volume or whatever
you know
these sorts of little
like quirky things we all have and um
uh oh i'm so yeah it's just this thing
about me you know
when it generally gives you anxiety and
you allow it to really become part of
your identity and you allow it to
genuinely affect you and it's now
negatively affecting your relationships
and um
i mean there's nothing wrong with having
a personality but uh when you start to
notice these things are unhelpful you
know what
we start to notice that you
maybe you don't want to identify with
someone with depression maybe you
haven't been to a doctor and he's told
you i have or you have depression you're
that you have
such and such you have such and such
here's you know that's we think that's
the only way that we
confirm we have something we have this
uh this disease or this sickness
you know
man i i mean i don't think you should go
around self-diagnosing yourself after uh
you know a couple reddit threads but uh
there there is
listen man
we're
we're all human this is part of being a
human this these are parts of
the experiences that i have
in you know within my consciousness
in my in my head you know
where is it is it floating around here
the experiences that we have
are a byproduct of our modern culture
our byproduct of
how
how and what a human is like what you
know even specifically like how are
americans in such way how
uh the the series of
events and teachings
and experiences
that i had as i was growing up in
certain certain years certain
detrimental years
shape who i am shape what i experience
shape how i solve problems they shape
how i
uh
contemplate my own existence they shape
how i
show up in the world they shape my
reactions we kind of have this weird
feeling
in the western world and it's no fault
of our own
um but we kind of have this weird
feeling that we like arrived on planet
earth
uh
like in a spaceship and
we're being taken care of by like a a
government or you know the there are
powers who know everything
and they are planning
out our life but we were born with
absolute complete
free will
as completed individuals and regardless
of what happens to us whenever when
we're adolescents or teen or even you
know in your 20s or 30s
it doesn't affect who we are and how we
show up because we just are this person
and we just deal with what happens to
life you know but we really are
you know if you really think deeply on
evolution um
which i think is a healthy exercise you
know you really think about how
our lungs don't work if we don't have
trees right like what are we breathing
in where do we get oxygen so why are we
considering ourselves separate than
a piece of us that must exist
trees in oxygen did not exist we would
not exist right so we kind of separate
ourselves we kind of compartmentalize
ourselves into these
little
separate
you know we we we act like we are on
earth not of earth
um
and and
we we kind of you know when we grow up
reading all these books all these uh um
you know
in class you're reading textbooks in
your and your your teachers are the
authority so they're teaching you
um
and you assume you know when you're
young especially you see like dude this
person literally knows like they're a
teacher and then you know you kind of
get older and
you're like oh wait i never really
thought about like okay of course they
don't sleep here huh right you know
remember having those like goofy
thoughts when you start to think about
what is a teacher and then you get older
um and you start
you know when i started getting like a
few years into my 20s i remember i
started having people around me and
people that i've been friends with since
i was a kid they'd become teachers and
i'm like
oh like
so you're like you're a teacher now and
at first you're like well you're a
teacher and you start thinking
oh yeah okay actually i'd probably do it
you do a pretty good job and then you
kind of remember
yeah now they're human okay so my
teachers were probably pretty human too
and you start to really think about you
know your teachers were actually your
age you know
i remember i had teachers who were like
25 years old and when i was 23 i'm like
huh
i had teacher i think you'd think
they're so on this pedestal well we also
kind of think about that when it comes
to like anybody in control of
money or anybody with power or
i know even saying the word government
has a lot of uh annotation on it that
kind of like puts our mind into
somewhere um what i'm not really trying
to bring up
uh
the structure of what it means to like
exist and grow up and be a human and
come out of
this giant rock hurling through space
you know
this thing that is called evolution that
we
our understanding you know we do
understand a lot of this very deeply but
you know this might be news to you but
we don't know everything like there is i
mean there's literally a thing called a
theory of everything and it is a
consistently evolving
no-answer answer that like all these
you know very intelligent people and
physicists and
philosophers are trying to
understand like we're trying to
understand what is consciousness what is
it like to be something
it's like a
you know kind of a brushstroke of what
consciousness means to have an
experience
we don't know there's not some dude
this may
i i promise this is important uh this i
know this seems like too far-fetched or
too left-field to have anything to do
with depression and anxiety but truly
understanding what you are and
not how you got here but
how
[Music]
your experience
of
yourself
is
man how do i word it because learning
about yourself learning
the history what we know so far and i'm
not even saying like what i've learned
and what i've studied and what i've um
read about is like the capital t truth
like this is the only one way i'm
telling you when you start to explore
any of these kind of forks when it comes
to philosophy and evolution in biology
and what are you and what is you know
you never would get into this kind of
god side of things but i'm not talking
about god religion god i'm talking about
uh
the god that pops in your head i'm
talking about the man with the beard in
the clouds that a lot of us
unconsciously think about when we hear
the words like god i'm talking about
i'm talking about
the core
of
ultimate
love
imagine
love continually going like uh
infinite
infinite love
i mean i think even the word love has so
much annotation on it let me back up
let's back up
i apologize i'm trying to
my notes are just my intention
i didn't want to overthink this
and so my intentions are really to just
explain anxiety and depression in a way
that helps people
those who have it and those who
do not you know i uh
i kind of started i was talking about
how
what depression isn't isn't you know
it's not just extreme sadness
it is this
something is wrong
something feels wrong you know it's it's
a
we're kind of this
chemical factory where this where this
uh
there's all these different things you
know if you take a say a vitamin d pill
think of it okay well vitamin d is a
supplement that you buy
well no vitamin d is a vitamin
is
vitamin d is a process in which
the
sun
affects an organism
and it's a
vital part of
our structure so if you take out vitamin
d
things start to go wrong in the
human factory
so
we
we misunderstand
droughts
it's a you know if we think of ourselves
like a chemical factor if we think of
ourselves
it's
it's a something is wrong i am missing
something you know right now for me to
speak to you there's all sorts of
there's you know millions and billions
of cells and all these things happening
and all these things firing and all
these things uh uh
you know combusting and combining and
duplicating and depleting and releasing
you know
we can't see it but our you know our
pores are releasing certain things uh
there's these synapses firing it's all
going on that's all happening um
when you're depressed it feels like
something in that process
is like [__] up it feels like
something in that process is uh
like
like just not working just busted and
the problem is a lot of the problem that
adds to it is is we identify with that
and we feel like an idiot because of
that we feel like that's something like
that's our fault you know we
right now you're sitting there you know
breathing and your your heart is pumping
and your blood is moving on there's all
these you know billions of things that
are happening within you
uh
and you you don't take credit for them
you don't say oh that's me pumping my
heart like i'm consciously pumping my
heart i'm conscious consciously
remembering to breathe you know
so
but but there's this thing with
depression and anxiety and a lot of
illnesses and a lot of mental health
stuff that
when it starts to happen
we take credit for it we
make ourselves feel bad
for having
these bad thoughts we make ourselves
feel bad for experiencing
inadequacy for
not being able to handle whatever is
going on for being anxious you know it's
this it's this big cycle uh uh
depression is kind of and then the
situation is like yeah of course this is
happening and anxiety is uh i i can't
handle this happening
so
there's this
there's this problem with the eye with
the constant um
this constant
attachment to
the it's this this reacting it's how
he's saying you know i have if you have
an intrusive thought you might have a
little tick afterwards like you think of
uh as you're driving down the freeway or
you're in the pasture seat of a car like
uh imagine if i lean my head out the
side of this car and just put my eyeball
on the grate as we're going 75 miles an
hour that would [__] hurt and then
you go i don't think that that's what a
crazy person would think about right now
you're literally in a car with someone
that you enjoy you're in the car with
your family like let's not think about
putting our eyeball against the side of
that barricade
um
if you've never had an intrusive thought
that probably sounds like a crazy crazy
thing to uh experience but that's what
intrusive thoughts are uh or like hey
can i hold your baby and you're just
thinking like i could chuck this baby
and not in a jokingly way you're like
almost afraid that your body may react
and just chuck that baby or something
you become fearful you have a response
to a thought the response to the thought
is what gets you sticky the response to
the thought is what you have to start
saying
nah nah
i don't want to think that
i'm not going to think that anymore what
what's something that you that
that i could put in its place or what's
what's a response to that you know
even even backing up even identifying
saying i don't want to think that i
don't think that's even helpful i think
even just saying
uh uh oh there my mind goes again
you know there there i am i had a
counselor one time um
she told me to think of this was
actually helpful [__] she told me to
think of
think of yourself like when you're
throwing a pity party when you're being
depressed when you're like being obtuse
and you notice it and you have this
awareness and then you're like well
dude i suck
i am an idiot and whatever um
start to
start to treat yourself like your
depressed self your your
bummer mood self you know that that dude
who doesn't show up
as um
you know the perfect partner
for
for your fam for your wife or the
perfect father for your for your son and
daughter or the perfect uncle or the
perfect friend or whatever you know the
this um this
you know
when you're when you're showing up and
you're noticing i'm being my depressed
self you have this awareness like okay
i'm doing the sad thing again talk to
yourself like that's what the counselor
said talk to yourself like
you're a drunk friend
imagine you're out with your homie
and
you two are having some drinks and your
homie has more than you and they get a
little slosh and they kind of had a
rough week and they're you know they
they lose it they start crying you know
we know how it gets with the booze
sometimes it'll poke you it's easy it
gets it's an antidepressant or it's it's
a depressant rather uh
you know and say your friends started
crying and they're like i don't know man
i've just really been going through a
lot lately and um you know so and so is
it left me and you know whatever maybe
they're sad they're getting down on
their self what do you say to them
you're gonna be like
are you gonna say you
[__] [__] man up you need to shape
up like bro get over it or
you're a depressed idiot or why are you
thinking or you're incapable or you know
what what does our mind tell us what
does your mind tell you maybe it's
different than the [__] that mind tells
me you know mine happens to be brutal
and specific and very mean sometimes you
know maybe yours is similar
would you talk to your friend your drunk
friend
calling him an idiot judging him having
a reaction to what he's experiencing
he's experiencing sadness would you
label him in a certain way or would you
say
i hear you bro
that's all right buddy
let's get you home let's get you some
water let's get you a [__] delicious
grilled cheese
that's what you get your crying drunk
friend it's a grilled cheese sandwich by
the way um
you know
and it sounds so overly obvious right
like of course you wouldn't talk to your
friend like that but we'd speak to
ourselves in that way the
response
to
the thought in the first place
becomes
like where our ego where our personality
where identity like really digs in
where it really
makes us feel bad about having those
thoughts about experiencing what we're
currently experiencing we put a label on
it we try to we bring out our
report card and we put f minus you suck
boom like bro you don't have to do that
you could
you know oh i'm noticing okay instead of
like you're a dumb [__] you talk to
yourself your internal dialogue is a bit
more um
sweet
friendly supportive you know you got to
start treating yourself like you would a
friend who needs help you know this is
part of the human experience you know
and this might feel stupid this might
feel silly that's part of what comes
with depression a lot of what comes with
depression is
it feeling fake
yeah
it feels so fake it feels contrived it
feels like you're
a
[__] boy it feels like you uh are
incapable of
experiencing bad emotions
uh
it feels like everyone else has their
[__] in luck and like your life is way
harder and you're just really confused
at how everyone is not completely
suffering at all times because that's
how it feels like it is in your head
it feels fake
when you get to coming around to
admitting you have depression and making
you have suicidal ideation admitting
that you have um intrusive thoughts
admitting that you have negativity
extreme crippling anxiety you know a lot
of this
i think especially when it comes for a
man i mean for me
it's uh
it feels very
like
like it's it's such a it's it's beyond
vulnerable but you are
um
it feels weak it feels definitely weak
but it's not it's actually is a form of
it's actually a a psychological form of
bravery um to kind of stand up to your
depressed
anxious mind and go dude
it's it's all right like okay
something's going on here like we're
gonna have to change paths whatever i'm
thinking about whatever i'm doing yeah i
listen i'm hearing that lesson loud and
clear i'm gonna take it i'm gonna grab
by the horns let's go
i'll handle it you know but
uh it's
you know
i should i should probably do this in
another
video
actually no
going to keep going
i i think this is part of it so
depression so i was diagnosed with
was first diagnosed with major
depressive disorder when i had first
gone in i mean it really you fill out
you fill out a questionnaire you check
some boxes
uh you kind of
a lot of it is kind of like figuring out
or coming to terms with or looking at
like did you have some childhood trauma
you know they have you they do a um
cbt
is it the cognitive behavioral therapy
obviously have you fill out this thing
and it's like my parents were divorced
when i was younger um i was raped i was
uh poor i couldn't afford whatever we
were evicted like you kind of have like
these
i don't know exactly but i don't
remember exactly but you you check off
these things and you have like a score
at the bottom of that you know it's kind
of experience going to the doctor and
when you have depression
and then you have a conversation that
you know for me it was
certainly less than ten eight seven
minutes
uh and before you know it you know you
prescribe this antidepressant you're
kind of trying to explain to this doctor
like i don't know what it is i just like
feel really
sad and my body hurts and i hate
everything and i want to
die a lot
uh and you're like looking at him really
funny please solve my problems and he
says yes sir i know the answer for that
uh there's this
uh pharmaceutical company who
uh gives me a bonus each year if i
prescribe enough of the you know
the way that we
diagnose depression is
super dumb and shitty and i don't think
that we understand it or even try to
understand it but what we have is this
medical
you know establishment that is
what you do it's this place that you go
to when your arm is hanging there and
you need surgery but we also are
bringing people with mental health
problems to to these places and it's
just completely a [__] show and it sucks
um
that's certainly my opinion and we can
fistfight about it if you agree or or
disagree so
i'll have a debate
uh
um
so i got diagnosed with
so through this questionnaire through
this
short conversation i was diagnosed at
first with major depressive disorder he
prescribed me some ssris
which are um
you know
like a serotonin uh
reuptake inhibitor
they just basically start to mess with
your brain chemicals and so i tried a
few different ones uh they kept upping
my dose
i felt completely [__] out of my mind
um
listen
these do help a lot of people there's
low doses of certain things that like
don't have such uh
obstructive effects on the brain but we
you know the research around this is
really the long-term research around
this and what it really does to our
brain and what it does to like our
psychological experience of ourselves
and the world
it's not heavily it's not as heavily
researched as you think it should be
it's not as full proof is
it's just not great um
so i was diagnosed with a major
depressive disorder tried a few was at a
really high dose um i was the point
where i'm just feeling zombied out i was
uh i was pushed over into
my suicidal ideation i was no longer i
didn't have like the fear around it i
had this like a blah numbness of course
so
like putting a
physically putting a loaded gun to my
head was like it didn't freak me out i
felt nothing it was like in in noticing
that
i couldn't have a reaction or like an
emotion to
that
and it it just
oh my god it was just this terrible
feeling um
it was like a feeling of nothingness you
almost like wish you were sad
it was super strange
um and then i had a bunch of side
effects uh and i had a bunch of
you know
i was going through a lot of
psychological crazy [__] anyway like uh
i'm already a pretty weird dude and this
was definitely like a few i'm actually
like just coming out of this last couple
years of my life of kind of insanity i
think last few years
and still still a bit in it for sure i'm
just as i gain more distance i start to
kind of understand and i kind of start
to like recoup some of the information
that i learned from myself and
through reading and listening to stuff
so
um
uh
so
major depressive disorder
lexapro
so i was also diagnosed with bipolar
depression
which i mean we hear the word this is
another one we hear the word bipolar and
we're immediately like people are like
okay so you're going to freak out and
stab people suddenly or you're very
uh unstable you know there's this the
psychiatric conditions
the way they're painted in our head
schizophrenia any any of this stuff
multiple personality disorder
multiplicity
all this stuff
this is another thing that you have to
notice in your head it's painted as this
like weird like hollywood videos or
hollywood video hollywood
movies and uh kind of like
what we were taught we were growing up
what our parents were taught what they
passed down to us you know they only
have the information they were given
we're kind of
we misunderstand a lot of this stuff you
know we we think of
this condition is
the crazy person screaming at the bus
stop you know it's it's this is way
different you know back in the day
something like schizophrenia for example
um if you showed signs of being
schizophrenic when you were younger you
would actually be sent to the like
village shaman to go live and learn how
to be a shaman
it is the way that your brain works or
the way that whatever you've got going
on internally psychologically
doesn't fit with the way that culture
society
um
our
capitalistic marketplace of of being it
doesn't fit with that it's a weird it's
it's too fringy it's it's uh it doesn't
make sense it makes people uncomfortable
it's a
you know it's this this crazy if you
call someone crazy if you you can
disregard them you can
you can instantly other them and it
makes you feel safe about how you are
saying
um
[Music]
but uh yeah
you know it really is this kind of like
learned madness that we have um
uh
i'm terribly going
going off path and in a bit all over the
place but i i do
think that
it helps
i'm sure it will spark conversations at
the very least
um i think that the way in which i have
experienced
conversation in long lectures myself
these sorts of like rambling to no ends
were some of the most profound
sentences that i would end up hearing so
i guess i will
try to
oh my god
antidepressants
[Music]
so when
i what is it about antidepressant okay
so i was diagnosed and what's important
here
the things that are important out of
what i'm trying to say here being
diagnosed with these things um is kind
of like you have to take you have to dig
things into your own hands you have to
do your own research you have to learn
about how your own mind works because
the people if you go to the doctors if
you go to
you know even some counselors and
therapists you know bless bless them
each and every one of them for sure
but they
they are also kind of like your teachers
you know remember um
they're just kind of people who
you know they certainly have their own
experience and there is you know people
who are uh you know far left feel
different and and i will say better
at this at truly understanding and and
through not checking the boxes not
not learning everything they learned
from studies in books and um
from data
from
uh
non-fiction
ways of understanding um
the human experience and sadness and
depression and anxiety
you know they they only know what the
what they were taught
in what they've experienced you know
maybe their personal experience has
brought them um
full circle but a lot of this a lot of
this
a lot of our
damn
you're going to have to help yourself i
mean that that's like that's what i'm
getting at is
you have to understand what's going i
mean it's kind of like the same thing
when it comes to fitness
is we have all these diets and we this
is another arrival thing that we're kind
of trained to is is is is
diets and fitness we're like okay i need
to lose 20 pounds once i lose 20 pounds
then i never have to like then i'm good
i don't even like what i don't have to
think about what i eat or what i do or
how i physically move my body and
whatnot
we just get to the next goal post you
know it's kind of the way that we're
taught to think remember you know follow
this carrot on a stick get from get from
elementary school to middle school and
then up to high school and college and
then you'll you know do this
it's it's really just
this
incorrect
um uh
perception of
kind of
it has to be a sustainability has to be
like a lifestyle it has to be like you
don't have to
become obsessed with depression and
anxiety and talking about it and like
that's all you do and that's all you
consume and you just like read millions
of books about it and whatever like this
is i mean i love doing all this stuff
because this one i needed at the
beginning i had to get into this i had
to uh
like dive head first into what's going
on because it was it was that or pulled
the trigger you know it was it was i'm
going to die if i don't do something
like i am
practically dead
with my inability and my like
not doing anything like these doctors
are not helping me i end up like cold
turkey quitting my antidepressants this
is years and years ago
and oh my god i was just just a total
mess and i think that there was
psychological effects like the way that
i
um
i had a lot of like depersonalization
derealization i had a lot of cognitive
dissonance i had a lot of
disassociative attacks
um uh maybe taxes yeah sure an attack
like um
my brain would just happen bro i mean
this was this was for a while after i
got off the antidepressant split or
literal years after um and i still
i mean i think that i had permanent
effects i think i had permanent things
happen to me by just throwing random
you know
antidepressants and [__] at my brain
i mean
not that not that i'm a perfect uh body
is my temple you know i put it i put
worse things in my
in my nasal cavity that's for sure
um
so
you know it really it really does take
this is not something that other people
can solve for you this is not your fault
but it is your responsibility if you're
experiencing anxiety and depression it's
on you baby
it's you and only you you have to take
care of it i mean if you got a loved one
if you got a family if you got friends
if you got people who could support you
know even your boss at work if they're
like yo i get it i understand you um you
know head home today yeah i don't know
whatever if you got people who
understand you that's a blessing but
really really really if you have
depression and anxiety it's uh it's on
you and i know that that's something
that people are almost like no don't say
that like well
you know there's this weird we can't
talk about certain things you got to say
the correct things when you're dealing
with someone um with depression and
anxiety and and i feel like
we need to open up the conversation we
need to not have fear we need to not
filter ourselves about this [__] we need
to have we need to personally share our
experience we need to not justify our
[__] we need to
not stay small in our ego we need to not
find
things that we can identify with and we
latch on and then protect anybody who
comes for that part of our identity
these are things that can be
in some way in some form
understood and you know
i don't like to use the word solved here
but there is a um
there's an understanding of
a lot of this depression and anxiety
stuff that you can get to through
knowledge through learning through
philosophy through learn listening to
other people speak about it through um
having actual open conversations without
the fear without the armor you know with
you know our [__] so bite size is so
quick but i mean if you really had
um
you know maybe or you're you're a
teenager and you're really close to your
mom but like she doesn't understand she
doesn't know that you're depressed like
if you just
sat down
and
uh you know just had hours worth of
conversation or an hour worth of
conversation you know no phones nobody
else no fronts no [__] you know no
obligations nowhere to be like really
just a
hey you know
i love you like the person across the
cross in the room like i love you
we got to talk about this i'm having
like i can't handle this on my own i
can't navigate this on my own because
when it's in our head cavity when it's
just bouncing around in our dang head we
don't really get
we don't really get like the the
different perspectives you know we keep
justifying our [__] our our [__]
our depression
starts to
um you know we identify with our
depression we start listening to that
that um mean voice and we start thinking
that's truth and and you know we start
we start uh believing the whisperings of
the devil you know we you know instead
of experiencing um
experiencing that feeling of being
the the homie to yourself to your drunk
friend you know to be like it's okay bro
you know it's having that that little
flicker of of god that's within each of
us that little flicker of love that's
what within each of us that little
that little
you know
like
[__] you nihilism you ain't taking me
down you know like wherever that comes
from wherever we can like get up out of
the dust like any time we've ever done
it we forget about the millions of times
we've done it and we've like gotten
ourselves out of bed and we didn't want
to and we like pulled ourselves we did
one more rep and we uh
we challenge ourselves to go talk to
that girl like that that that desire to
be more to experience love to be present
to to
say yes to
to step into that light you know that's
such a natural thing it's such a natural
way of being supposed to be our natural
way of being
you know listening to that
giving power to that it starts to have a
domino effect starts to have a snowball
effect where
you start what you do is what you always
do you know in this world we're all
we're evolution is moving some way this
this way that we are
existing the way that it is to be is
going a direction you know it's it's
moving at some momentum atrophy is a
real thing if you sit there's a guy
who's he's has his arm up like this and
he's devoted to never put it down he's
got a pinky up or something like that
and his his arm has become this like
tiny little frail stuck little like
stale breadstick looking thing you know
and it's just like that's what happens
if you you know if you go to the gym and
you boom boom boom look at time is
moving we're projecting we're going
through space everything is fluid life
is momentum it is moving if you do some
bicep curls you start to build muscle
you know
you you have to
fuel and listen to the correct person in
here you know you have to listen to the
good wolf you have to believe the good
wolf you have to say uh no to the devil
you know it's uh uh
don't don't let my don't let my wording
of devil and god uh sway you wrong the
there is something that happens in your
brain in a lot of our understandings of
these words that is is an incorrect
lie of what these things really are like
it doesn't have to have anything to do
with religion here this is just a part
of what it means to be a human you know
there is a spiritual aspect of every
single human this is just language but
it's there's a piece within you that
is
life and love that says yes that that
pushes forward that chooses to go that
chooses to be something rather than a
nothing that
finds delight in
the
uh
single light in the middle of
of of a chaotic infinity you know um
uh
there is
there's
you you you fuel that side of you you
you you gass up that good wolf you gass
up that superhero side of yourself that
like
i can handle this i'm not perfect i'm
human um but you know it takes that
nihilistic view of your future that like
i'm never gonna amount to anything
[__] and it says
you know what maybe i will maybe i'm
gonna die maybe i'm gonna die trying you
know maybe i'm gonna i'm gonna
i'm gonna
i believe that i could be those things
like why not try you know you start
listening to that that superhero that
that you know you got to give yourself a
cape you got to notice you got to bring
awareness awareness is the huge thing
right you got to notice that this is
happening because you'll be identifying
with your thoughts you'll be
synced up thinking that everything that
is being thought all these thoughts that
are happening you're thinking that they
all are you and i'm such an idiot i'm
such a [__] and i suck and and my my
kids are better off without me and i'm
terrible in my job you know whatever it
is
this this extreme
this heaviness that comes with you know
being depressed and being anxious uh it
is it
it
is
given fuel you know you you fuel this
thing up you fire this thing up you uh
by listening to it by by not saying i
see you fool i see you devil i see you
uh i see you depressed jake you know you
know what i mean you got to um you got
to you got to
you got to feed the good wolf i mean
that really is
okay okay and listen like this isn't
some [__] that i read right
feeding the good wolf um
even like this is something that i had
to really discover i think i think uh
the the part i mentioned about
depression feeling fake feeling
contrived uh
the
believing in yourself thing the like
self-love thing the listening to the
dude with the superhero cape not the
nihilistic you know sad sad guy
being there for the sad guy okay uh yeah
but what we're actually gonna do is
we're gonna be positive because uh i
know that if i feed this wolf it's gonna
blah blah
you know that
is something i discovered like it was it
took me a while because you have to keep
laying this brick by brick this every
you know every time you have a thought
every day that this comes up some days
are worse than others but you just got
to keep bricking by bricking and
it it
it
it starts to it really does have
momentum you kind of build yourself into
the non-depressed person the non-anxious
person the person who has a situation
happen and has like a little bit of a
wedge of
um
you know
gentle thought before reactivity
uh
you know
there's a there is a happening and your
response to it and your response to it
gets trained
by
being
and not not just overly positive not
putting blinders on to the world like
you know
if you're stressed about your bills the
bills are still coming baby but like
you know you kind of get this but i can
handle it i'm gonna trust
that like i've taken care of everything
before in the past i'm i'm 30 years old
i've handled it before i'm gonna damn
well handle it again let's go what do i
need to do
you know let's let's act or um you know
there is even a side of that that isn't
letting go like i trust
um i trust that this will work out you
know i i have done everything i i can i
have prepared myself in in every which
way there's no sense in being anxious
about this thing that is inevitably
going going to
uh
not maybe not inevitably going to happen
in such a way but there is this event
that is coming and happening and i am uh
dealing with this thing
i i i see that it is not helpful for me
and my life
to
listen to the worst case scenario
view of of what may happen in the future
i see that that is unhelpful
so i choose to
[Music]
recognize
allow
but
shelf not listen to allow to float away
let it be as the beatles would say you
know the uh
let it let it pass by you know in the
meditation we talk about a lot of we
talk a lot about um
observing and noting okay that's a
thought that's a feeling yeah you know
you're sitting on the bench watching the
freeway you're sitting on the bench
watching the cars you're not on the
freeway hustling and just experiencing
all the emotion of the cars and i am
this and i am that you
watch what the mind does you watch the
the brains uh madness that we all have
of being a human it's just like a sense
you've probably heard um the third eye
the mind's eye it's the sixth sense
um uh i do want to do a video on the
third eye because when i when i first
had heard about it i thought it was like
the coolest creepiest like illuminati
what's that like it's just really it is
a really cool concept but it's very
confusing to understand at the beginning
uh
uh but our sixth sense you know
right now as you when you if you think
about a meditative state you're just
sitting here observing what is happening
like you are not
you aren't your eyesight you aren't
your experience of smell
you can observe the body
having this experience
and it's not a you it's not a like i'm
not saying jake is observing it is
as a conscious experience
as consciousness itself
i
watch
the
let's say five six senses let's say five
senses so
as i'm sitting here
i feel
i have the feeling of touch
of my lips touching one another i have
the feeling of my my shirt on my skin of
my bottom on my on my cushion of my feet
on the floor
um that i'm feeling i can hear
what's what's something that i hear far
away what's something that i hear close
what have i gotten used to what have i
completely blocked out and and forgotten
that was there can i hear a freeway in
the distance can i hear an airplane can
i hear my neighbor's gonna hear music
can i hear
my air conditioner you know there's all
these layers of sound sound you you got
touch you have sound you have your
eyesight i can see
there is a a designated uh
uh oh i'm blinking on a lot of the
concepts for visual acuity but there's a
like a focal point you're focusing on
one thing right now i'm focusing on this
camera but there's also this peripheral
out here right like i can see i'm not
watching it but i can see out of the
corner of my eye i can see my hands and
i'm aware that i'm doing this
you can see
up above all these things that you kind
of ignore because you have a conscious
experience that points at what in
physical reality is important to what
you need to meet your you know hierarchy
of needs whatever it is that you're
searching to to have whatever need you
are certainly have met at this moment so
you have your vision
you can see far you can see close
you have smell
you could smell deeply you can you can
even kind of back to touch and feeling
you can feel what your body does when
you smell
and you can even kind of just without
breathing in just if you subtly
just
notice the smell that's already in your
nose you know just by breathing through
through your nose you kind of notice
um
taste you can
what do we know what do you taste if you
had a cup of coffee uh
if you had you know food recently do you
taste the remnants of the food have you
brushed your teeth
you know you don't have to do that but
but there is taste happening and what
you're doing is you're bringing your
awareness to these things these five
senses in the sixth sense that i was
mentioning is thought this is something
that is kind of complicated it's kind of
hard for us to understand it's kind of
the root of meditation a lot of ways is
the observation of thought not becoming
identified with it
again the way we grew up the way the
western world is the way the western
world has made
us into who we are the teachings of
uh this this current moment of the
zeitgeist has made us
um
kind of
we just have so much momentum we don't
we don't stop and notice all of these
things uh we don't stop and notice that
the same way
sound is happening i'm not saying let me
hear my air conditioner
it's just there right you know as soon
as i
as soon as i s you know kind of sit back
in my mind in a sense kind of
relax into it
the sound is is simply happening you
know there there is a happening that has
a reformation
of of of my eardrums vibrating and it's
creating what we what we call sound
at the same time the mind
as you listen and things are just
happening the mind is also just
happening
thoughts are just happening it is part
of
being a human it's part of having an
experience each human on this planet has
this
happening but the problem is we over
identify with we we think we are the
thoughts we think that we are the
stream
imagine if if you're
you know when you're listening to
someone mow a lawn if you're sitting
here right now and your neighbor is
mowing their lawn
you know you hear it you don't think i
am
the lawn mower mowing the lawn
i am the neighbor mowing the you know
oh that's a sound that's happening
and then you have a reaction
maybe if uh imagine a grumpy person
leans his head out the window turn that
[__] off it's it's three o'clock in the
morning whatever uh or someone who
uh
you know is very calm and they don't
other you know the happenings of what
other people are doing sound wise don't
really affect them
they may just
neighbors mowing their lawn they're back
to crocheting whatever it you know
there's a reaction you know and what you
need to do is train your reaction
to of course your five senses to what
you see to what you hear these are these
are you know basic
you know practices of emotional
intelligence but really we
try to think of
thoughts in the mind as a sense in which
you
[Music]
needn't intertwine
that rhymed i think
but
you start treating just just as
everything in your visual environment
you don't react to every single thing
you choose what to react to what things
are important to me in this very moment
to meet my needs
what things are very important for me to
listen to as the mind produces thoughts
and and feelings and um
and uh uh
you know
ideas you know these ideas just kind of
uh
percolate out of nowhere they kind of
come up out of nowhere and and
though we don't get to choose
you know how
we certain we don't get to choose when
we you know shut our mind off we don't
shut our mind off
or stop the flow of thoughts but we can
choose to not
you know it's almost like not listening
to certain ones or something uh
it's
yeah it is this lack of identification
with thought i hate to just consistently
restate the same thing but that really
is what it is
uh
and and
you know
this wasn't taught to us
this is not something that like our
parents and grandparents knew about the
depression rates and the in the
suicide rates anxiety rate the amount of
people have anxiety the amount of
prescription drugs that are um
uh
you know given out for all these certain
all these things these days it's
continually rising like
listen man if you're listening to this
[__] or you have a family member
listening to this [__] or you're you
know your mom is depressed so you're
watching this trying to figure out like
what's up with her
um and try to like emphasize with her
and try to understand her condition or
something you know like seriously you're
not alone i know you hear it that's a
buzz thing you know you're not alone in
your thoughts you know you have uh
whatever it's it really is though
we feel so these these depressive uh
overly nihilistic bummer thoughts really
have this stickiness to him that is like
dude i am a freak
i am a like evil gross demon like
man
like if everyone's
secrets and internal
life and thoughts
were laid out
truth you know and that was our truth
rather than our you know fictitious
k-fade
civilization
uh um
we you know
i think that
we would all have such a laugh
we would all just laugh ourselves to
death if we if we truly saw and
understood into each other's minds you
know
we walk as if it's so put together out
here but it's just madness in inside and
we can't even admit it you know we can't
even um
we can't even
this is like the ego protects us from
from
even really like course correcting
because it's so far off
um
okay so
i think i want to try to round out but i
think i i want to hit anxiety just
specifically and i really want to offer
this goodness
for
how to handle anxiety attacks and how to
reduce anxiety
um like what i really want to
because i
i'd still deal with depression i still
have um you know out of the diagnosis i
feel like i believe the
the um the bipolar depression it really
is
some days i
i open my eyes and it's like oh [__]
dude
yikes like this is this is uh
this is one of those days i think you
know like
strap up let's roll like let's
you know we got work to do today is
gonna be
a lot of work in my mind
to
keep it
between the lines
um so i still have those and i'm working
on it i'm consistently trying all these
new like supplements and um
reading these new books and you know
a lot of meditation a lot of yoga a lot
of breath work whatever but
anxiety
is something that i really
don't experience that much anymore i
really
i mean certainly compared i used to have
a anxiety attacks panic attacks
everybody kind of has their own version
of the east eastern this is another
thing that we feel like
like don't [__] tell anybody i just
had that like because it's completely
embarrassing it's com it's a complete
like
fragmentation of
all of what we are in our image and our
logic and our sense-making is just
completely out the damn window when it
comes to panic attacks and we think that
our body is
uh like we think you know i mean people
check themselves into the er
consistently because they're having a
panic attack and i think it's a heart
attack i mean this is like a very common
thing i know tons of people who had this
exact experience
and i would have conversations with them
and they come back and you know they
believe the doctor of course they're not
going to believe my crazy ass but they
believe the damn doctor with his lab
coat he's like yeah you had a panic
attack and i i didn't know and
uh
let me i i hope i don't make anyone feel
bad for having a panic attack and going
to the doctor
it really is just this thing that's like
pretty intense it really is like a you
know it could be a big deal panic attack
anxiety attack
um it's kind of your inability to deal
with what's happening you know a lot of
anxiety uh is born from
not being
thinking we are unable to
handle not having our
preference
so let me restate that
not getting your preference
creates anxiety
and your
presumption that you cannot handle
not having your preference
and like consistently identifying with
that
creates this loop of anxiety
so
like
you have to bring in awareness and and
logic and that wedge you have to bring
that into
the same thing that when you know if
you're talking to a sad depressed friend
who's drunk and he's just like hammering
you know i'm an idiot you're like you're
not an idiot buddy you're fine you're
just drunk it's okay man we're fine
you kind of have that same with it with
anxiety though it's harder to grasp in
those moments because anxiety has like a
manic like radic uh uh
frantic
feeling to it
um but but it is a
like okay what what's really happening
right now you know you get present you
use your five senses to get present
and you realize that like there's no
there's no torpedo coming there's no
lion coming because look at what what's
happening when you're having an anxiety
attack why are you feeling like all
these these panicky feelings it's the
the smaller part of your brain the fear
response is being turned on you know
this uh like through evolution we have
this reptilian part of our brain that
gets turned on it gets activated and it
starts
prioritizing
you know our conscious thought is is
certain things happen in the brain in
different areas and we have certain
experiences and thoughts
i'm not saying they're exactly
correlated but they are
coinciding
and we
you know
we have these for a reason we where
we're
you know
we were running around with moon cloths
and spears you know for like hundreds of
thousands of years
uh
you know or
yeah a long time you know we're what we
are
was built this thing that came after
monkeys and we started like
having communities and working together
and like foraging for food we started
farming we started saving food and
storing food all these things that
started to happen
from from monkeys you know
think about how many freaking years we
really were running around
if you hear a rustling over there in the
bushes
you have to think
that might be a lion so i need to have a
quick
i'm going to survive the best my species
is going to continue to repopulate this
earth evolution
if i have a quick response with my spear
ready to go is that a lion over there is
that a tiger over there i just heard
that rustling so you have this thing
that activates we have all these
chemicals that happen this brain stem
this thing
uh
what is it what is it the amygdala
i think i [__] up when i try to get
overly overly sciencey i think i need to
just uh remain in a philosophical uh uh
standpoint of explanation
so so we have a lion over here and we
have a bodily response and then our
experience
you know our thoughts and
everything is trying to solve it rapidly
trying to find the patterns what's going
on i i'm in fear you know i'm anxious
about this thing i'm afraid of this
thing that's going to happen you know
we now have
the ability for that to happen to
activate this thing that we have
in our human body to respond to actual
threats that was very very helpful and
is very very good
up until like a couple hundred years ago
a hundred years ago i mean really iphone
came out in 2007
like
not that long ago for what we are
we had these fear responses we had these
anxiety we had
uh
immediately get to a heightened state of
awareness because you need to be able to
attack this line that you just heard
rustling in the bushes did you just see
out of the corner of your eye like a
little piece of tan
is that a lion let's protect my family
we got to survive you know this has been
happening for a long time well
the
the modern world the modern
culture
has things that happened to us you know
the system is kind of gamed at us a lot
when it comes to you know social media
and technology and in in the internet uh
there's a lot of things that activate
the same thing that would be activated
when a lion is about to attack attack us
that same thing is activated
because it's
fills someone's pockets because
if i can get you to react you're going
to stay on my site more if i can get you
to react you're going to play this game
more if i can get you to react you have
it's it's more memorable you know
just just as i was talking about our
visual acuity you know you're looking at
this thing i'm looking at the camera i'm
kind of ignoring these things around
here my peripheral
it's the same thing
there is if this is just green over here
this is just green nature this is this
there's no line there's no threat
there's no reason for me to pinpoint and
look in and figure out what's going on
there's just something i can okay it's
safe
our
we're not going to pay it mind we're not
going to divert our attention to that
because it's not it's just enough it's
okay it's safety we're fine we don't
have to worry about that well
that same way
of presenting
content the same way of presenting
people trying to sell us things are
capitalistic like
put this in front of you get a reaction
because it makes it more memorable for
you show
these certain colors because
through evolution we have
different reactions to different
colors because we only see them in such
environments imagine if you had lived in
the amazon
and you never saw you know
if you think about how insane a tiger
would look like how much it would really
stand out or like a white tiger or
something i mean i i don't know if
they're in the
sun
uh uh
like that would that would really stand
out you know so
uh there's a reason in which th there's
there's an evolutionary reason why we
would respond in these in these such
ways but now our whole world this whole
thing
is
activating that fear response in you as
this thing that came after an ape or you
know whatever your beliefs are i think i
think uh uh i'm i think a lot of people
you know would agree uh on evolution in
in some senses um
this
part of your brain is being activated
you're anxious because
you think that there is a you're trying
to perceive a threat
you have anxiety because you think
that this lion is about to pounce on
your neck you know and you need to have
anxiety to be ready for it so you can
kill him with a spear and protect your
fam
so
the world is kind of against us in this
way you know especially again this
modern
if you're someone who's on
you know
if you're someone who watches the news
this is being played against you very
heavily um
you're thinking about all these things
that may happen you're afraid of this
thing that is coming this person caused
this thing to happen over here on this
side of the world so it's definitely
going to make this thing happen and lo
and behold all the things that you've
been so stressed out about have never
[__] happened
you think about everything you've ever
felt extreme anxiousness about did it
happen
this is how this is this is how this
works this is what goes on we forget
this though like we don't notice we're
so mad where our thoughts are just
just going so crazy that
these happenings
these happenings don't ever really
happen but we spent a lot of time uh
ruminating and right in in
fearing that they might happen fearing
for the the lion or the tiger to pounce
we are
uh uh trying to protect ourselves we're
looking out for these threats we're
trying to protect our family trying to
protect our community trying to protect
our loved ones even our like tribalistic
groups we're trying to not only belong
with them uh but we're trying to find
the enemies it seems like a helpful
thing right find the enemies figure out
who they are so they don't trick us so
they don't uh you know
steal our baby or when they only you
know take our food supply or
you know there there is the
the
there's the
you know primitive
part of having a human body
you know and we have this consciousness
projected
into it or from it or whatever the hell
is going on here
it's
something that
we can't blame ourselves for not
understanding you know
it's something that you know this seems
a lot of stuff seems like really obvious
but
there is something about it that is is
uh
liberating to
take some time and just okay
that really is what's going on huh damn
um just just kind of sit with it again
our mind we're constantly wrapped up in
the the click corals of of the
neurological dance you know it's uh
it's
okay so
i got around the corner with this
anxiety thing the breath is a huge part
of
anxiety the breath is a huge huge huge
part
bring awareness to this you have to
start noticing
where you're breathing when you're
breathing how often you're breathing how
fast you're breathing how slow you're
breathing are you breathing through your
nasals are you breathing through your
mouth
uh are you
wearing a mask way too damn much i don't
think anybody should be wearing any damn
ass at this point but
watch what the mask do to your breathing
these masks i think are actually making
us more anxious which raises cortisol
levels which shuts down
think about it when you're in fear when
you think that a lion or a tiger is
about to pounce do you think that your
body is like now is the optimal time to
grow your fingernails
now's the best time to digest that bag
of sour patch kids that you ate earlier
no no you shut down a lot of stuff
inside your body because you're
prioritizing the blood being sent to
like your extremities
you're you're prioritizing
when you're stimulated like this with a
fear response or even like essential
response there's things that are shut
down that are not working in the same
way because your body is prioritizing
all this energy to this said things
because it has to be able to be reactive
and protect itself because none of that
chip matters if you're dead so
the
the digestive system is not working when
you're in a fear response the
fingernails and toenails are not growing
when you're in a
fear response your cortisol levels are
high you actually i would say your
immune system is probably compromised
your immune system is probably if we had
to say what is a hundred percent
working immune system it is working at
tip-top shapes say someone who's like
completely athletic and taking all the
right vitamins they're eating all the
right things and the breathing the right
air whatever and their immune system is
this that's 100
do you think your immune system is at
your hundred percent when
you're about to stab a
tiger a bear a lion
oh my with a spear
no that's not what happens you are
prioritizing the chemicals in your body
are prioritizing certain things this is
out of your control this is not what you
you're not beating your heart you're not
breathing in the air to your lungs it's
an unconscious background task
we take credit for certain things but
this is really just like a happening and
we are
there's an ego experiencing it so the
the happenings of
the body
the
um
so what we need to so the breathing we
need to
when we're doing these things if you're
you're scared
you know
listen where's your breath if you
pretend you're scared right right now go
go
what does your body do your butt cheeks
clench up your toes move your fingers
move your shoulders come up
your eyebrows like you have all this
tension but also the breath escapes and
it gets small in your chest
okay what is a very relaxed low heart
rate monk look like
he's so relaxed he's zen
his voice is not even up here in his
head it's down here and it's in his
belly it's deeper
the air
it's not all over my head it's not my
chest i'm relaxed right
in the air i'm breathing through my
diaphragm you want to you want to be
when you notice that your breath is up
high when you notice that your breath is
short i mean notice that your breath
when you notice you're holding your
breath all these things that are very
obvious don't overthink this like if
you're not breathing slow there is
numbers that you can look up but if
you're not breathing
slow out and slow in
you are in a state of
some sort of heightened awareness and
it's unnecessary for most of our states
of being nowadays um
we have like all this
[__] this all this like it's it's you're
in the middle of times square in new
york and there's just this color and
it's like look at this and it's just
respond to this and it's this guy is the
enemy and [__] these people are
trying to kill you and it's all this
stuff the stimuli whatever
of the modern world is keeping us
small breath
shoulders tensed up
the response of of everything that we're
doing
uh
you know our mind is like seeing it as
real experiencing it as real and so it's
making our
bodily functions react in a certain way
so what you have to do is you have to
bring this awareness and keep talking
about this this uh
this
you have to bring this realizing that
your breath is not where it needs to be
and you have to bring it down into the
diaphragm you need to be breathing
primarily in and out of your nose
and you need to be breathing out super
slow you'll be breathing in super slow
again it's going to feel weird it's
going to feel unnatural it's going to be
hard to concentrate on that even but
i'm sure that people if you have anxiety
i'm sure people have told you about
breath working for i'm sure breathing
techniques uh have you tried this
whatever whatever
this is again it's great there is a
break glass in case of emergency
um side of anxiety attacks and breathing
techniques and like okay i need to
you know i need to wim hof to get this
way you know
there is this
there is a response when you need it but
generally
when you're alive existing right now as
you're watching this video as you're
going to work as you're getting in the
shower as you're getting out of the
shower as you're
wiping off your mouth after you just
brushed your teeth as you're
texting as you're scrolling through
social media as you're laying in bed
before bed as you're laying in bed in
the morning which you shouldn't do
what is your breath look like where is
where is the center of your breath
where's the tension at in your body this
is also something that's really
accompanied with breath
you need to be breathing through your
diaphragm which is you know your belly
low belly you can really
if someone said take the deepest deepest
breath that you've taken all day you can
find a
you know you could find it really deep
in there there's just been air stale
sitting there man it's all just just
stale bum stinky air sitting there
because you there's there's just
chilling down there there's all this you
know co2 chilling down there and you got
all this
you're just breathing up here because of
all this stimuli
so the breath is one of the most
important things you know yoga
meditation this helps train the breath
this helps train the the you know not
train the breath i don't think that's
the best word uh yoga is union with the
breath yoga's union with the body um
so
the when you when you do yoga when you
meditate it again it trains you what you
do is what you're always doing like i
said right
you're training yourself in this way you
bring alertness and awareness to the
breath to breathing and tense tense
what what am i
physically responding to
that i'm mentally picturing and is that
true
in the present moment is that actually
happening
or is my creative wonderful brilliant
brain
filling in the blanks of what it thinks
that it's that it should be doing is it
trying to protect me thank you brain for
trying to protect me but there's no lie
and there's no there's no tiger we don't
need protection right now okay
so
you notice it's happening you notice
you're breathing this way you notice
that you're tense
and you go oh okay okay look
there's no line
and maybe you know give yourself
30 seconds of breath 20 give yourself
four in and four out like just real slow
i mean that's definitely that's going to
be less than a minute
something like that you you just
and feel where the breath is don't be
caught up in like trying to get rid of
the thoughts that are coming
thoughts happen just like sound thoughts
happen
you don't stop them from happening
meditation is not sitting down stopping
your mind from having thoughts that
doesn't happen unless you're at a
certain stage of enlightenment
you just observe that they're happening
okay i'm still having that thought i
don't need to get into the ring and
wrestle with it i don't need to put on
my boxing gloves and fight that thought
and tell it that it's untrue whatever i
can go oh okay that's just a thought
when you physically respond
you mentally respond it seriously helps
it's again it's another thing that feels
fake you're having an anxiety attack
you're having this [__] that's happening
you're stressed out you're yelling at
people you're whatever it feels
justified you're like don't why aren't
you all doing this exact same thing no
no it's your chemicals and it's your
responsibility to take care of it it's
not your fault but it's your
responsibility you have to
okay i understand that i'm not going to
be my most helpful self to these people
around me to myself
by responding in such a way so how do i
readjust all right let's be
remember let's be gentle with ourself
let's be
okay well the mind's doing that thing
and what's really going on here let's
breathe my breathing in
and again
there is a break glass in case of
emergency with a lot of this breathing
stuff but breathing is something you're
doing all the time breathing something
you've already been doing it really is
this magic up down left right x square
triangle like cheat code to life
that
is right it's the most in front of us
thing ever there's a lot you're probably
hearing a lot about breath work and
breathing techniques and stuff nowadays
it's buzzfeed word and there's wim hof
and all these things but the the core
bit is
the breath
uh is a direct correlation to our
physical
state in our mental uh
um projection or understanding of what
we think is happening so we don't have
to
we need to
be dealing with reality like if you are
if you're watching a movie if you're
watching fashion fast and the furious
it's fun to have like oh my chemicals
are moving all around i'm excited and
i'm at the edge of my seat you know and
you're and you're smiling and you're
experiencing what they're experiencing
on there but it's not actually a
happening you're not actually about to
be
hit by you know a 69 dodge charger it's
happening in the movie and you get to
experience it but look at look at what
your body does oh you gasp
your mind thinks that it's actually
happening you could do the same thing
without watching a physical movie you
could be thinking about what might be
happening and your body is responding to
it like you're in fast and furious
what's the truth about fast and furious
okay i'm scared or maybe i'm in a scary
movie i'm i'm reactive to this but you
can leave the theater and
it's not there what's the truth about it
okay the truth is i'm in a dim hallway
it's rather quiet uh
that lady is sweeping and she was very
polite when i talked to early so the
actual reality of what the scary movie
or the fast and the furious thing that
was going on inside there
it's just
you you have a bodily reaction you have
your breath changes your your thoughts
about it change and sometimes these have
reminiscent uh uh you know trails of of
what you're thinking you know if you're
getting a heightened response sometimes
it's not as easy as i mean most time
it's not as easy as just oh yeah forget
about it you know you're gonna have this
you go to a scary movie
the dark's a little more scary that
night ain't it be aware of what you're
consuming if you have this consistently
consistent you know fear of the dark in
this analogy
what scary movies are you watching you
know if you have fear of bad other if
you have fear of these bad guys if you
if you
think this thing is going to happen what
are you consuming what's convincing you
because why aren't all the people around
you in the same state of fear because
they're not consuming what you're
consuming they're not reading what
you're what you're reading they're not
talking to the same people you're
talking to so
if you're at a point where
your depression your anxiety these are
things that humans experience
uh if if if if
you're having these experience uh
if you're having these experiences
you are a human congratulations
it'd be like that sometimes
um
it's okay
uh
and and believe me as someone who
has been through the ringer i have my
certain lows i have had my
immense i've had plenty of anxiety
attacks i've had a lot of suicidal
ideation i have depression i have all
this [__] i've been through a lot of it
and it's been many many years for me
you're not alone
i think it gets better
because this is more that carried on a
stick you're going to arrive
i will say
knowledge is power
and
who you are
now or you think yourself to be
now
must fall away
for
who you will become
[Music]
to happen
uh
don't be afraid of
realizing that enough is enough don't be
afraid of realizing that like damn it
dude
this depression thing
i'm experiencing this sadness thing
this
let's not buy more black clothes
let's not listen to the music louder
let's not find that comfort and sadness
that's really there oh and i mean
comfort there is a comfort in depression
and it sucks and it's dirty and you
don't want to get out of your bed
but
you
have no idea what you're capable of in
the future you have no idea
you don't know the love that you get to
experience perhaps in the future you
don't know the the the joyous moments
that you still have left how many more
years do you have left
you don't have to spend them sad you can
start to understand like don't just
someone help me
a doctor help me counselor help me
it's okay to do all those things and
there's no shame in it
we're all trying to figure this thing
out we're all trying to learn our own
paths
but walking down a path whatever speaks
at you most of these things you know
getting better
it starts to snowball
it feels fake
it does feel fake it feels contrived it
feels like
lame it's
you know there there's a
sadness and a letting go of your old
self that has to start to take place
there's a
detachment from all these thoughts
there's a scariness to all of it because
this is all like
what like turning internal has not been
trained to do but
you know
we haven't we haven't been taught how to
open doors from the inside
um but i'm telling you knowledge
listening to people talk about these
things listening to people conversate
about them there's so many podcasts
there's so many youtube videos uh
you know
sitting there i don't know what to do i
can't do anything
damn it youtube go on youtube and just
search the most basic thing
watch what jumps at you scroll for a
little bit maybe there's a hot girl on
the fourth thumbnail and she's talking
about depression for 12 minutes and
oh cool maybe that's interesting start
there what gets suggested after that you
got to just start consuming better
content don't consume content to
numb the feeling that you're going
through consume content that helps you
deal with and understand and take by the
horns and [__] handle what's going on
because you can handle it you absolutely
can handle it we are capable of
incredible things as humans but we're
we're made to feel small we're made to
feel incapable or made to feel like we
need someone to come save us and
you know
cut that leash cut the tether
and you're going to flow fine you know
you're going to be all right you can
handle it
the person you are right this second
maybe he can't handle it but the person
you are becoming
every damn second after that
he's more and more capable she's more
and more capable
there's a video about depression and
anxiety
i hope my ramblings help somebody uh i
will continue to
do the things that i do
there it is
i'm gonna go eat some chicken tacos
peace out love yourselves y'all